A Guide to the American Association of University Women, Loudoun Branch Records, 1973-1998
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
American Association of University Women, Loudoun Branch Records 1973-1998
Thomas Balch Library
M 056
The collection contains the records of American Association of University Women, Loudoun Branch from 1973-1998.
American Association of University Women, Loudoun Branch
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Michael MacIntyre, Leesburg, VA.
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2002.0010
Historical Information
A group of 15 college alumnae met in 1881 to discuss creating an organization that would bring together women college graduates, provide an opportunity for them to utilize their training, and encourage women to pursue higher education. The Association of Collegiate Alumnae (ACA) was formally organized in 1882 with 65 members. Areas of advocacy included educational opportunities for girls and women, funding for schools and libraries, and child labor laws. Starting in 1884 the organization admitted branches, local groups that supported the national mission while working on areas of interest to their constituents. ACA merged with the Southern Association of College Women to form the American Association of University Women (AAUW) in 1921. AAUW currently has over 100,000 members.
Early in 1973, the Virginia Branch of AAUW approached Karen Jones (n.d.) about establishing a Loudoun County branch of the organization. 26 women met on 28 February, electing temporary officers and approving by-laws to create Leesburg Area, Virginia Branch of the American Association of University Women, known locally as the Loudoun Area Branch. The name changed officially to Loudoun Branch in 1997. Initial topics of interest included growth and development, education, cultural activities, and legal and civic rights of women. In addition to advocacy activities, the branch organized dinners, lectures, and cultural outings.
AAUW sponsored a report in 1991 called "Shortchanging Girls, Shortchanging America," which used a nationwide poll to assess educational experiences and interest in math and science among boys and girls. The inequity for girls spurred the Loudoun Area Branch to plan a math and science fair for girls, with goals of increasing young women's interest in the subjects and provide them with an opportunity to meet women working in those fields. Math & Science Conference for Girls was held at Loudoun County High School 16 May 1992, and became an annual event.
Membership in the branch peaked in 1980 with 85 members. After years of declining membership in the 1980s and 1990s, the Loudoun Branch disbanded in August of 1998.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the records of American Association of University Women, Loudoun Branch from 1973-1998. It includes minutes, newsletters, membership lists, newspaper articles, and financial reports. It also contains documentation of the organization's disbandment in 1998. Items in a "magnet" scrapbook were removed and placed in folders; pages 9 and 10 were blank.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
AAUW, http://www.aauw.org/about/, accessed 16 November 2010.
American Association of University Women, Loudoun Branch Records, 1973-1998 (M 056), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
None
Contents List
- By-laws 1981-1987 (Box:folder 1:1)
- Policy sheet n.d. (Box:folder 1:2)
- Executive meeting minutes 1973-1978 (Box:folder 1:3)
- Minutes February 1973-May 1976 (Box:folder 1:4)
- Minutes June 1978-May 1980 (Box:folder 1:5)
- Minutes June 1980-May 1982 (Box:folder 1:6)
- Minutes September 1982-April 1987 (Box:folder 1:7)
- Minutes November 1989-February 1992 (Box:folder 1:8)
- Minutes March 1995-October 1997 (Box:folder 1:9)
- Financial reports 1981-1985, 1997 (Box:folder 1:10)
- Secretary information and by-laws 1987-1991 (Box:folder 1:11)
- Membership lists 1973-1997 (Box:folder 1:12)
- Branch disbandment1998 (Box:folder 1:13)
- Newsletters June 1978-April 1980 (Box:folder 1:14)
- Newsletters September 1980-Spring 1982 (Box:folder 2:1)
- Newsletters September 1982-September 1986 (Box:folder 2:2)
- Newsletters November 1987-April 1992 (Box:folder 2:3)
- Award, Outstanding Member Retentionn.d. (Box:folder 2:4)
- Math & Science Conference for Middle School Girls 1997-1998 (Box:folder 2:5)
- AAUW Teacher of the Year Award1997 (Box:folder 2:6)
- Photographs - Halloween Parade1994 (Box:folder 2:7)
- Photograph - unidentifiedn.d. (Box:folder 2:8)
- Newspaper articles 1978-1986 (Box:folder 2:9)
- Scrapbook, pg. 11984-1986 (Box:folder 2:10)
- Scrapbook, pg. 21984-1986 (Box:folder 2:11)
- Scrapbook, pg. 31984-1986 (Box:folder 2:12)
- Scrapbook, pg. 41984-1986 (Box:folder 2:13)
- Scrapbook, pg. 51984-1986 (Box:folder 2:14)
- Scrapbook, pg. 61984-1986 (Box:folder 2:15)
- Scrapbook, pg. 71984-1986 (Box:folder 2:16)
- Scrapbook, pg. 81984-1986 (Box:folder 2:17)
- Scrapbook, pg. 111984-1986 (Box:folder 2:18)